hey everyone welcome back to another
lesson in the stores car automation
course
in this particular video I am going to
talk about conditional loops and how you
can use them in your Tosca test cases
the first Loop which we are going to
talk about is the while loop
now this is a pretty common Loop
statement which is used in all the
different languages and if you have
worked in this already you would know
what a while loop does the logic is
pretty much the same in Tosca so in
Tosca if it checks for the condition and
if it is fulfilled test steps within
that Loop object are run repeatedly
until the condition is no longer
satisfied
so we are going to look at it using an
example and this is how it will look
like so what basically I'm doing is I'm
trying to do the repetitions logic using
a while loop now we have seen how we can
use the repetition property to repeat
our test steps uh number of times right
so we can do that using Loop statements
so what I'm doing here is I'm setting a
repetition buffer and then I'm using the
while loop to check a condition whether
that repetition is less than 5. if it is
not less than 5 then it will exit the
loop if it is less than 5 then it will
do some calculation and repeat the loop
so this looping will continue until this
condition is not satisfied or the
repetition becomes more than 5 it will
exit the loop and it will go into the
next test step so this is what basically
we'll be doing using the while loop
another important thing to note here is
while loop also has a property called
maximum repetitions now this is to avoid
infinite loops and Tosca by default sets
this value to 30 but you can change it
so this is uh what is about while loop
now let's look at our example well we'll
try to build a test case using this
while loop and it will be based on this
particular flowchart
okay so I'm going to create a new test
case here and I'm just going to call it
a while loop
okay
and here I am going to demonstrate how
you can use your while loop so as we saw
in our flowchart that we want to set a
variable or you can in Tosca terms it is
known as buffer okay we are going to
talk about buffer in a different video
I'm not going to explain a lot about it
but it is like a variable which you can
use throughout your test case okay so
I'm going to add a test step here to set
a buffer value
and this is the t-box set buffer module
so here you have to provide a buffer
name I am going to call it R okay and
I'm going to set the value to zero okay
so this is my D box set buffer
and after this I am going to add or
create a while loop okay and that you
can do right click on this test case and
there you will find create a while
statement
okay so that will create the while
statement with a condition and with a
loop okay so in the condition we have to
specify some condition
um and that is to check whether the
repetition buffer is less than a certain
value okay
so again I'm going to add a desktop here
I am going to say uh evaluate okay so
I'm going to use the t-box evaluation
tool where I can put an expression and
which will be evaluated or verified okay
so in this case I'm going to use my
buffer okay so I'll say B of R and I
will say this will be less than 5.
okay so as you can see this is the
expression which will be evaluated by
the t-box module
so this is our condition and then in
Loop if this condition is satisfied we
need to add something okay
so here again I am going to use the set
buffer
Okay so
what I'm going to do is do some
calculation here
so I'll put it R and
I'm going to use a function called math
okay so this is a Tosca function which
you can use to do some calculations
basically
and inside this I'm going to use my
buffer which I have created so B of R
okay
and then I am going to add 1 to this
particular buffer every time this Loop
is executed
okay
and then let's close this and let's
close this okay
so this is our calculation which we are
doing we are using the math function to
basically add a number or plus one to
this buffer every time this Loop is
executed okay
so this is our Loop and this condition
and this is the buffer okay uh you can
change these names here which I have set
so you can give some useful names here
okay
so I can call it a set repetition
okay and here I can say
check reputation
less than five
and here I can say
calculate
repetitions
okay so this is how our flowchart looked
and that is what I have done here okay
okay just a minute I I have to give the
test step not the
so I will say here set repetition
okay so this is the step name uh I
mistakenly I have put it in my buffer so
that buffer should be R otherwise this
expression won't work okay
the other thing I wanted to show you is
for this while statement so if you go to
properties you will see there is a
property called maximum repetitions
whose value is 30 I can change it okay
let's go ahead and execute this test
case so go and run in scratchbook
and it should hardly take a few seconds
to do this it's not doing much here
right so here uh we are setting the
repetition buffer it will go into the
while loop and you can see there are
six repetitions right so the loop is
continuing
um it is going to check for this
condition yeah it's evaluated to true so
it will go into the loop uh and it will
basically do that calculation right in
the last uh repetition the expression
would be valuated to false and hence it
will exit out of the loop so this is how
you can use while loop or you can use it
inside your test case to basically do
any kind of configuration or basically
put some logic around your test cases or
test scenarios
now let's talk about the next step of
loop which is called the do while loop
now it's pretty similar to while loop
but there is a little difference the way
it works okay so in this the test steps
within the loop object are run
repeatedly until the condition is no
longer fulfilled
and the major difference between a while
loop and a do while loop is
the statement would be at least executed
once in a do while loop even if this
condition is not satisfied because the
condition would be satisfied later on
right so this calculate reputation would
at least execute once before it checks
the condition but it's the other way
around in the while loop okay so this is
how the flowchart looks like pretty
similar only thing is the loop Begins by
doing the calculation and then it checks
for the condition
here also uh the maximum repetitions
property is present
to avoid infinite loops and the default
value is set to 30.
now coming back to Tosca you can easily
do the same thing using the do while
loop with what we have done with the
while loop right so I'll just show you
how you can do this right so let's
create another test case and we can give
it a do while loop name okay in inside
this right uh again you can set the
buffer and you can do things like set
repetition here so I will just copy
I'll just copy this step here right
because it's the same thing with what we
want to do we want to set the buffer for
repetition
and then basically we need to add a do
while statement here okay so how you can
do that right click and you can see here
create do statement you can also use the
shortcut Ctrl n and Ctrl d
okay so I'm going to add a do while loop
here so it will have a dough Loop and a
do condition okay and basically uh again
you can set this check repetition
you have to put it under condition
okay and this calculate repetition you
have to put under Loop
so that's how quickly you can create the
same test case basically using the do
while loop okay so I've just copied the
steps here
uh this will calculate the repetition
and this will check for the reputation
okay
so let's quickly uh execute this and
check
the results would be pretty much similar
okay the only difference uh being the
way it is executed okay so you can see
here uh here it is calculating uh and
then it is going into the condition
right so it is evaluating that
expression and it is it will repeat
until this expression is false okay
so in the last repetition it is going to
say 5 is less than 5 evaluated false so
it will exit the loop and go into the
next step
okay so the number of repetitions are
different uh in a do while loop and a
while loop so depending on your test
scenario you have to decide which one
you want to use okay but these are two
different conditional Loops which you
can use in Tosca to make your test cases
more flexible and to handle more
scenarios
so this was all about conditional Loops
stay tuned for more Tosca videos coming
up pretty soon
we are trying to upload a new Tasker
video every Friday so watch out for
these videos or every Friday on our
Channel